<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England's alarm, or, A most humble declaration, address and fervent petition to His Most Excellent Majesty, Charles the Second, King of Great Britain and Ireland, and to his most honourable and grand council the Parliament of England, as also to the city of London, and the whole nation in general concerning the great overtures, catastrophe's and grand occurrences about to inundate and pour in upon us as the judgments of Almighty God upon Antichrist and his adherents, and the pride, nauseancy and errour of professors in the years 1680 and 1681 / written by a true lover of the true Protestant religion and of his tottering poor native country of England, Johannes Philanglus.</title>
            <author>Johannes, Philanglus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38374</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2939</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4913</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12791847</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12791847</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93953</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38374)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93953)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 379:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England's alarm, or, A most humble declaration, address and fervent petition to His Most Excellent Majesty, Charles the Second, King of Great Britain and Ireland, and to his most honourable and grand council the Parliament of England, as also to the city of London, and the whole nation in general concerning the great overtures, catastrophe's and grand occurrences about to inundate and pour in upon us as the judgments of Almighty God upon Antichrist and his adherents, and the pride, nauseancy and errour of professors in the years 1680 and 1681 / written by a true lover of the true Protestant religion and of his tottering poor native country of England, Johannes Philanglus.</title>
                  <author>Johannes, Philanglus.</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Pasham ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93953:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93953:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>England's Alarm: OR, A moſt Humble DECLARATION, ADDRESS, and fervent PETITION, To his Moſt Excellent MAJESTY Charles the Second, King of Great <hi>BRITAIN</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> AND To his moſt Honourable and Grand Council The PARLIAMENT of <hi>ENGLAND;</hi> AS ALSO To the CITY of <hi>LONDON,</hi> AND The whole NATION in general. CONCERNING The great Overtures, Cataſtrophe's, and grand Occurrences about to inundate and pour in upon us, as the Judgments of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God upon Antichriſt and his Adherents, and the Pride, Nauſeancy, and Errour of Profeſſors, in the years 1680 and 1681.</p>
            <p>Written by a true Lover of the true Proteſtant Religion, and of his Tottering poor Native Country of <hi>England. Johannes Philanglus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Paſham</hi> in <hi>Fleet-lane.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:93953:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93953:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>England's Alarm.</head>
            <div type="address">
               <head>TO THE KING.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Moſt Excellent and Dread Soveraign,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE meaneſt Creatures have acceſs and admittance to the Throne of the King of kings, by the Bloud of Jeſus; may I, the meaneſt of your Subjects, have admittance to your Temporal Throne, by the Dreads and horrible Fears of the ſecret Effuſion of your own and our Bloud, by the unpreven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Conſpiracy of Bloud-thirſty Papiſts. The meaneſt Star, as it hath dependance on, and influence from the Sun, hath liberty to dart forth its Nocturnal Beams, when great <hi>Phoebus,</hi> the <hi>Titan</hi> of the World, ſubmerſes his refulgent Rays on the <hi>Neptune</hi>-waves; and now your glorious and Princely Rays are feared dayly to ſet continually, in the Horizon and <hi>Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunian</hi>-Sea of Popiſh and Jeſuitical Subtilty, and bloudy Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Shall faithful Subjects be afraid of a Frown, when Church, State, and Crown are, by Papal Violence, Tumbling down? —<hi>Inter majora ſydera minora lucerent.</hi> The poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Subject in the Primitive Raigns of the glorious Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> have been permitted to cry, in times of extremity, <hi>Help, O King!</hi> 2 Sam. 14.4. And though your magnificent Majeſty be ambiently attended with ſo many Stars of the firſt magnitude, yet a poor <hi>Micaiah</hi> may prophecy to the King, and have a clearer proſpect of the Coeleſtial Councels
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93953:3"/>upon the heavenly Throne, than the <hi>Zedekiah</hi>'s with their iron horns, 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 22.11.24. though he be fed with Bread and Water till theſe Euroclydons be blown over. So, moſt excellent and glorious Prince, I beg Pardon as proſtrate at your moſt Soveraign feet, for this act of ſeeming-preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, while I acknowledge my ſelf nothing; yet in the hand of God, things that are not, may inſtruct things that are. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, the preſent Neceſſity, the horrid and trembling ſounds of the Plot and Plotters Alarming my Ears, my obſequious duty to my King, and love to my Native Country, is the Womb that hath conceived and brought forth this Trembling Babe: Which, although in its Infancy, may, to the future admiration of the ſecureſt Lethargiſts in this Nation, be credited as a Child of Truth, by that time bright <hi>Phoebus</hi> hath twice mounted the twelve <hi>Herculean</hi> Pillars.</p>
               <p>I remember, it was aſſerted by that Reverend Biſhop <hi>James <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> ſometimes in <hi>Ireland,</hi> That thoſe Predictions that fell from him (moſt of which are fulfilled al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready) were imprinted and engraven on his Spirit: even ſo are theſe things that now I write to my Soveraign Lord the King and Country. And moreover, if it be true, or like to be true, that is reported to us by the Speech of the Dead, in Noctur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Viſions, as is famouſly reported by antient Philoſophers, as <hi>Artemidorus,</hi> and the famous Remembrances of <hi>Julius Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> his Warning before his Death and fatal Stab in the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate, <hi>cum multis aliis;</hi> then have I reaſon to fear the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of theſe things on my Spirit, and theſe ſcaring Viſions of the Night, which for ſome years paſt I have ſuſtained, concerning the Perſon and Crown of your Sacred Majeſty; and alſo of him and them who have raiſed the Thunder and Tempeſt in this our Horizon. As alſo the juſt fears we may have of the ſudden Fall of your Life and Crown, by the hand or hands of Papiſts. And that except your Majeſty be mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly defended by ſupream Providence, and the timely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions by his mighty hand; and alſo your Royal Adherence, and juſt and methodical Conjunction to your great Council the Parliament, and ſo joyntly removing the Nations Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and thoſe things offending the King of Kings, and timely and ſpeedily executing Juſtice upon the notorous Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93953:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>of your Majeſties Crown and State, and of the Church of Chriſt; it cannot be, but that before either your Majeſty or we are well aware, they you now by your boundleſs Clemency indulge beyond Neceſſity, will give the fatal ſtroak to your ſacred Life, and in yours, to all your Subjects, who have the Breaſt-plate of Chriſts Righteouſneſs upon them, and the marks of the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> caſhiered from you to the Conformiſts and Nonconformiſts; and that I trembling fear in the 1680th year. O! would your Majeſty pleaſe ſpeedily to extirpate out of your Royal Territories, and this City of <hi>London,</hi> all thoſe <hi>Amalekites</hi> that trouble <hi>Iſrael,</hi> (I mean the <hi>French</hi>) that devour and eat the bread out of your Subjects mouths; and may you ever remember, that King <hi>Saul</hi> for neglecting the Word of the Lord, and not totally deſtroying <hi>Amalek,</hi> had his life diſhonourably taken from him by a Chip of that block, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. compared with 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.13. Antiquity tells us, our Engliſh nation was never more bleſſed with Peace and Proſperity, than when the French Nation were conquered by us; as by <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth of famous memory, and <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth, who was crowned in <hi>Paris,</hi> and planted the Flower-de-luce in <hi>Englands</hi> garden: But now it is to be feared that the French King will be crowned not in the French, but our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh <hi>Paris (London)</hi> except the providence of the King of kings divert preſent occurrences, and the prudence of your moſt Excellent Majeſty, in happy Conjunction with your prudent Parliament, prevent it; which that you may, the God of Heaven grant.</p>
               <p>'Tis a Curſe in Gods Word, to be governed or counſelled by the Spirit of <hi>Jezabel,</hi> or by a wicked woman, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 3.12.15, 16. Hence hath aroſe monſtrous Pride, and intolerable Oppreſſion, the very bane of Church and State. Who knows but by the hands of ſuch, your Majeſty may ſuſtain a Stab or fatal Stroak! And nothing would more draw the hearts of your Subjects up to the height of true joy, than if it may pleaſe your Majeſty to abandon ſuch morning-clouds from the Mountain of your Throne: O how glorious would the day ſhine! It is expreſsly ſaid by God, the King of kings, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.17. <hi>The King ſhall not multiply wives to himſelf, that his heart turn not away.</hi> And though <hi>Solomons</hi> Throne was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93953:4"/>eſtabliſhed by God himſelf, yet it was ſtrange women made his Crown to totter, and his Kingdom to rend aſunder. 'Tis the greateſt intereſt to Kings and Princes, to treat the Lords people kindly, who are ſtill by the Papiſts and Popiſh affected, called, in ſcorn and deriſion, <hi>Hereticks:</hi> for <hi>he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Kings for their ſakes,</hi> Pſal. 105.14, 15. 'Twas the <hi>Prodromus</hi> to the deſtruction of <hi>Ireland</hi> formerly (as ſays Dr. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi>) to adhere to the Principles and Patterns of Papiſts; nothing being true they hold, as ſaid the Martyr, but the Doctrine of the Trinity: for Free will, and general Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, now embraced by too many, is the Foundation of the Popiſh Kingdom, firſt brought into <hi>Rome</hi> in the fifth Century by <hi>Pelagius.</hi> 'Twas the haſtening the deſtruction of <hi>Ahaz</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 16. in that he joyned himſelf to the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> verſ. 7. Nothing can more ſuddenly ruine King and Kingdom, than joyning Affinity with Popiſh Princes, becauſe God hath determined to caſt that Mountain as a Mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone into the depths of the Sea, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. <hi>Jer.</hi> 50, &amp; 51. and they that will not come out of her when her hour comes, ſhall periſh with her without all peradventure. Beſides this, <hi>Ahaz</hi> goes to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> verſ. 10. and takes a faſhion of the Altar and the Worſhip, and ſends to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rijah</hi> the Prieſt for to take a pattern thereof; which, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8. cauſed the Lord to haſten his Judgments, under the figure of <hi>Maher-ſhalal-haſh-baz,</hi> make haſte to ſpoil, and to the prey make ſpeed. So verily will God make haſte to ruine that Kingdom that ſhall patternize their Worſhip, from the grand Idolatry of ſo impudent an Harlot, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is. Alas, our Sun is darkened with Popiſh Principles, our Moon turned into Bloud, our Stars fallen and falling from Heaven, the true Proteſtant Profeſſion and Principles; both Univerſities and Pulpits filled with the Roman Traſh that the Martyrs and Fathers of our Proteſtant Religion truely abhorred, and Gods word is ſilent in: while thoſe few Stars that remain in their Primitive Luſtre, are ſcoffingly called <hi>Calviniſts</hi> and <hi>Solifidians,</hi> as if Chriſt and his Apoſtles were not the Patrons of the ſame Doctrine.</p>
               <p>May your Majeſty be directed by the good Angels of God, to do what may preſerve your Life, prevent our Fears, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh your Throne, comfort the Proteſtant Churches of Chriſt,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93953:4"/>and glad the hearts of all your Subjects. Your Majeſty knows that the deſigne of Monarchy is to preſerve your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in it ſelf, not to betray it. For though thoſe things that God will not ſet up, be attempted in the breaſt of Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty it ſelf, yet it may not proſper, but will tumble down as <hi>Babel. In medio Conſiſtit Virtus.</hi> The way to make your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom everlaſting, and your Crown immovable, is to conſult Gods Word and Will, and execute his Commands, cheriſh his Church, his Doctrine and Truths; baniſh and ſubdue his Enemies; and make it the policy of the State, to aim at Gods Glory, the Nations Proſperity, and the Churches Comfort: by permitting the various Intereſts and Priviledges of King and People to glide ſweetly in their proper Channels, as Law, Reaſon, and Equity hath provided, from the Conſtitutions of Antiquity.</p>
               <closer>Vivat Rex, &amp; Vertitas.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="address">
               <head>To the PARLIAMENT, <hi>the great Council of</hi> England.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Noble Senators,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WHen you that are our great Repreſentatives, and the Pillars, Nerves, and Sinews of our Body-politick, have not a Being, it may be ſaid, that the People and Nation of <hi>England</hi> (during that <hi>Caſma</hi> and Gulf of Diſſolution) have alſo no Being. And how monſtrous would it be in the eye of Reaſon, and incommodious to our Intereſts and grand Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, at this juncture of Affairs eſpecially, to have a glorious Head without a Body to ſubſtitute it? But though yet you are not born into our Angelical Commonwealth, yet I hope you are conceived in the womb of the hearts of the beſt Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whoſe great Intereſt it will be to haſten the Birth with all poſſibility, and by a careful Midwifry to deliver ſafely that hopeful Child may cheriſh its aged Mother, and defend her from that Murderous Train of Popiſh Plotters, and Devils in grain: That you may have the Heart of Piety it ſelf, and the Tongues of Angels, to promote Juſtice and Verity; <hi>bovem in lingua nondum ut habeatis:</hi> That Bribes may be as remote from you, as the Eaſt from the Weſt, as Popiſh Cruelty is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93953:5"/>diſtant from <hi>England</hi>'s Felicity: And as it was once ſaid of the <hi>Belgick</hi> People, of their prudent management of great Affairs, ſo may it be practiſed by you; <hi>Dum neſciunt fingere poſſunt, quid autem agant ſtatim Statuunt.</hi> Noble Sirs, as it was ſaid in another Caſe, may be now ſaid to you in this preſent Caſe, <hi>Quid facitis, faxite Citiùs;</hi> if you be not nimble, the mangled walls of our old <hi>Carthage</hi> will be tumbled down, and the <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Whore ruſh in at both ends of the Town. And if bad Councel, or thwarting Providence, or Romiſh Policy, ſhould either prorogue your time, or diſſolve your being once more, 'tis paſt peradventure feared, we nor you ſhall live any longer, and your Ruines will make way for our Miſeries. O conſult God, begin at the Oracle not of <hi>Delphos,</hi> but Chriſt: Reſolve with <hi>Hannibal,</hi> when he was going over the <hi>Alps</hi> into <hi>Italy, Aut inveniam, aut viam faciam.</hi> Truely, Sirs, you muſt hew your ways through the Rocks, and meet your Enemies under ground, or they will quickly both you and us Confound. And, as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid to <hi>Malancthon,</hi> If we ſhall not boldly and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly do the Lords Work, he will remove us, and raiſe up o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; ſo ſay I to you, If through fear, cowardiſe, or ſloath, you ſhould outſleep three quarters of a year more, our Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will end, and your Work be finiſhed: Yet will God raiſe up others yet inviſible to deliver his redeemed, and work won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for us in our field of <hi>Zoan:</hi> for the Earthquake, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.11, 12, 13. is at hand, 1680 will go near to manifeſt it, and the time of the three days and half, the time of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Sackcloath and mourning ſtate, is near expiration; and God will call you up in a Cloud of protection, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26. <hi>ult.</hi> while he ſhakes the Earth and Earthly Profeſſions and Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and makes the Earth to diſcloſe her Bloud, and bring to nought things that are, by things that are not, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. and the Romiſh <hi>Philanax</hi> ſhall be caſt in the Sea like a Mill-ſtone, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more to riſe; and her Brats and Followers, and the Bloud of Chriſt, but their own dung and droſs, ſhall periſh with her: becauſe when they were called out, they refuſed the Wine, Milk, and Waters of Life, the marrow and fatneſs of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, for Traſh, Popiſh Ceremonies, and Jeſuitical Doctrines. And this let <hi>Sion</hi> expect 1681 or 1682, to 1685. Deliverance will come another way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="address">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:93953:5"/>
               <head>To the CITY of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>O, London, London!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MY Soul mourns for thee, like <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> Ezek 28. thou haſt been like the Garden of god, every precious ſtone was thy Covering; thy Tabrets and Pipes was prepared in thee in the day that thou waſt created. Thou that waſt the anointed Chorubin, thou waſt upon the holy Mountain of God. Thou haſt wallted up and down in the midſt of the ſtones of fire; thou haſt had the voice of the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in thee, when the dark places of thy Land was deſolate; but Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is found in thee. In thee is found fulneſs of Bread, Pride and Wantonneſs, Extortion, Whoredoms, Drunkenneſs, Errour, and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. None have partaken more of Chriſt, and none have more ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and abuſed Chriſt, and the means of Grace: and becauſe thy heart is lifted up, and thou ſaideſt I am as God, <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord, Behold, I am againſt thee, O</hi> London, <hi>I will cauſe</hi> (Ezek. 26.3.) <hi>many na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to come up againſt thee, as the ſea cauſes his waves and tydes to come up to thee. And they ſhall deſtroy they walls, and break down thy towers: God will ſcrape thy duſt from thee, and make thee like the top of the rock.</hi> And becauſe thy Children are ſettled up the Lees, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1. God ſhall ſearch thee with Candles, and purge thee with Nitre and Soap, and caſt thee into the Furnace, that his Sons among thee may be tryed. Neither will thy Gold or thy Silver preſerve thee in the day of wrath, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.18. becauſe thou haſt been wanton, and decked thy ſelf in thy Attires, while thy poor Brethren have wanted Bread, and Arraiment to cover their Nakedneſs. And thou haſt profeſſed a Faith that had nor love nor bowels in it; but haſt cried out, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66. with the Proud, Stand far off, for I am more holy, more rich, more honourable than thou; and haſt reſpected the perſons of the rich and great, while thou haſt contemned the brother of low degree: Therefore, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 3. ſhall thy Jewels and Ear-ring, thy Head-attires and Paintings, thy French faſhions, and uncivil and unſeemly Dreſſings, proſtrating thy ſelf to Strangers, and diſcovering thy Nakedneſs by thy French unſeemly Robes and Dreſſings, God will ſend thee (yea by that Nation) whoſe folly thou haſt impudently followed, Baldneſs for hair, Stink for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes, and Sack-cloath for cloathing; War for peace, and Bloud for water; till thou return and acknowledge thy iniquities, and break off thy whoredoms and impieties, and be found in the way of repentance. But for the hidden ones in thee, the Children of the Covenant, who have the Faith of Jeſus, and the Commandments of God, who have not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93953:6"/>exacted the labours, but freely followed the Lord the Lamb; and have cloathed the naked, and fed the hungry, and ſcorned the faſhions, and deſpiſed the glories, and have been transformed in the renewing of their minds; who have diſdained the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Garment and the wedge of Gold, the Lord will hide them in the hollow of his hand, and ſay to them, Come, my people, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26. into your ſeveral Chambers, until the indignation be over. But you that drink Wine in bowls, and ſport your ſelves on Beds of Ivory, while the afflictions of <hi>Joſeph</hi> are not minded, ſuddenly will come your Calamity, as the pains of a woman in Travel, and as the Storm and Thunder in a clear day. A day of wrath, a day of trouble and diſtreſs, a day of waſtneſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, a day of darkneſs and gloomineſs, and a day of clouds and thick darkneſs. And you, <hi>Canaphims</hi> and <hi>Kenites,</hi> that for your A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtical <hi>Self-interest,</hi> that God of the world, ſo you may keep but your Pride, your Honours and Gold, care not though you ſet to your ſlaviſh hands and help to pull down the Church and State, and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Bribes as Children) Plumb-ſtones; be it known to you, if God be true, a double portion of divine Vengeance ſhall be your lot in the day at hand. And note, that Unanimity, not Uniformity, is moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from Papiſtry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="address">
               <head>To the NATION in general.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Ah, England!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THou haſt had thy Name from thy Angelical State and Beauty, but thou art fallen like <hi>Lucifer.</hi> Thou waſt an inexhauſtible pit of Treaſure, and his Deviliſh Holineſs in quondam times hath licked his <hi>Neapolitan</hi> fingers of thy Sweetneſs: and now he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thy Delicacies, and would attempt to raviſh thy Wardrobes, and drain thee dry with his inſatiable Bucket; if for thy Iniquities thy God gives him leave. For the Pope, like the Devil his Father, cannot come one link of his chain, unleſs thy God ſuffer him, for thy unrepented Sins; and while thou art crying out againſt the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits and other the Incendiaries, thou forgetteſt to cry to him, whom by ſin and diſhonour thou haſt provoked to ſend the Wolf and the wild Boar of the <hi>Italian</hi> forreſt, into thy Vineyard. Remember, <hi>England,</hi> if thou art not mad drunk with the Whores Charms, how that thy Preaching-Miniſters are turn'd into dumb Dogs and ravening Wolves. And they bear rule by thy means, and thou loveſt to have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93953:6"/>it ſo, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.31. And you that are of the Eccleſiaſtick Function, that not long ſince, if you do remember, did caſt out the Labourers of the Lords work in the Lords Vineyard, and got the Fleece, and turned the Flock to the Devil, and ſet up your drunken, mad, <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian, Pelagian,</hi> and Pope-poiſoned Sons to enſnare the Flock. You hate the Pope, but have received Popery: Arminianiſm, Free-Will, General Redemption, Falling from Grace, denying a free, perſonal, eternal Election, are all hatched in Hell, and are the Popes founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that which the Martyrs abhorred, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in thoſe days Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts only aſſerted; and in your bringing in of this Serpent, of this Army of Vipers in the belly of the <hi>Trojan</hi> Horſe, painted o're to the Peoples view with a ſhew of Zeal, Religion and Purity, yet the ground of Popery in <hi>England,</hi> and of our Deſolation and Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and this brand will lye on you, Gentlemen, when <hi>England</hi> is wallowing in her bloud. And have raiſed up Perſecutions and Acts of Parliament againſt the Lord's Lambs, for ſerving their God, and preaching Chriſt to the People, whom you have famiſhed with your <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> diſhes, and driven them from poſt to pillar, while you ſuffered the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Leopard to lye in your houſes, in your Territories, and in your Pulpits. And now you are come up in remembrance before God, and ſhe (I mean the whore) whom you have adored and juſsled ſo nigh to, will juſsle you out of your States, Dignities, and Honours: for though you turn, ſhe'll no more truſt you, you ſhall burn. <hi>Behold, I am againſt thee, O thou moſt proud,</hi> Jer. 50.31. and 51.44. and you ſhall ſpew out again all the Dainties you have ſwallowed down by iniquity. Your Wall ſhall fall. Break off your Iniquities by Repentance, if happily the Lord may accept you, and turn to the Bloud of Jeſus, and acknowledge your Errours, your Covetouſneſs, your Perſecutions of Chriſts Lambs, your feeding your bellies, and famiſhing the Flock with Popiſh Traſh and dry Ceremonies; and caſt from thou that <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Garment you have beſpotted your ſelves with, and let not the duſt of an Idol lie in your Gowns, in your Families, in your Churches, and in your Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits. My Soul mourns for you, becauſe you have the name of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. O that you had the Spirit, and Doctrine, and Gifts of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. Gather your ſelves together, yea, gather together, O Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not deſirous, before the decree bring forth, before the day paſs as the Chaff, before the fierce anger of the Lord come upon you. Seek the Lord all ye meek of the Land, that have Chriſt's imputed Righteouſneſs for your Wedding-garment, and his Bloud alone for your Laver; It may be ye ſhall be bid in the day of the Lords fierce
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93953:7"/>anger, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2. Repent of your fulneſs of Goſpel-bread, your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saking the pure Doctrine of Chriſt and his Meſſengers, and giving heed to lyes and ſables: ever learning and running up and down, but never attaining to the faith of Gods Elect, and to the Love that covers a multitude of ſins; who juſtifie your ſelves, and cloak over your enmity, malice, and implacable ſpirits, with fair words and ſoft ſpeeches, and voluntary humility, while within you are Pride, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, Revenge, Luſt, and all manner of wanton filthineſs. The Lord hath made bare his holy arm, and will take away your Cloak that you have deceived with, and you ſhall ſeek from ſea to ſea for the pure Word you have contemned, with its diſpenſers, while you have laid out your money for that that is no bread, that is, not Chriſt And you ſhall know that the Lord hath ſpoken to you, but you have refuſed the ſtill Waters, and choſen the ſwift streams. There is no Peace to the wicked in their own righteouſneſs, out of Chriſt imputed Righteouſneſs; but it ſhall be well with the Righteouſ, even in the day of the greateſt diſtreſs. Then lift up your heads and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, for the day of your Redemption draws nigh. For in twenty four years to come, there ſhall be neither Pope, nor Popedomes, but the Lord ſhall reign in Mount <hi>Zion</hi> before his Antients glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
